<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-16T07:29:40+00:00</updated><id>https://yannbourgeois.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">New publication</title><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/papermolecol/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New publication"/><published>2025-08-01T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-01T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/papermolecol</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/papermolecol/"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to report that our publication on urban green anoles (<em>Anolis carolinensis</em>) has been published in open access in Molecular Ecology! We looked at the accumulation of mutation load, spatial isolation and signatures of adaptation in an urban population in New Orleans, compared to other localities nearby. One of the most striking result, which emerged from following a reviewer’s recommendation (<a href="https://kmwinchell.com/">Dr. Winchell</a>), was that the HOXC cluster fell in the middle of the strongest signal of association and differentiation we could observe! You can read the paper <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/mec.70057">here</a>, and access the scripts <a href="https://github.com/YannBourgeois/Scripts_urban_anolis_lowdepth">here</a>. I intend to turn this into a tutorial at some point, which may cover imputation without a reference panel. We used STITCH, which seems to work very well even with only 100 samples. I heard that it works well in haplotagging experiments, which provide phase information that helps reconstructing genotypes accurately.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="publication"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Article on urban adaptation in anoles published in Molecular Ecology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Review on introgression methods</title><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/review_interest/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Review on introgression methods"/><published>2025-07-26T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-26T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/review_interest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/review_interest/"><![CDATA[<p>Testing introgression, and whether it is adaptive, is a major research topic in evolutionary biology. This recent review is valuable, and I intend to add the methods they list to my list of methods. The article can be found <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tig.2025.07.001">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="method"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A good resource to be added to the methodspopgen tables.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ANR PRC ORIGAMIS funded</title><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/anrOphrys/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ANR PRC ORIGAMIS funded"/><published>2025-07-24T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-24T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/anrOphrys</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2025/anrOphrys/"><![CDATA[<p>Joris Bertrand (coordinator), Anaïs Gibert and I received an ANR PRC (collaborative research) to study speciation in <em>Ophrys</em> orchids. You can look at Joris and Anaïs research <a href="https://www.jorisbertrand.com/">here</a>. This project will tackle the challenge of population genomics of speciation in species with large genomes. We will focus on both SNPs and TEs. The funding should cover two post-doctoral researchers, stay tuned!</p> <p>The summary is reproduced below:</p> <p>Orchids in the genus Ophrys have a fascinating pollination strategy (sexual swindling). Their flowers mimic the visual, olfactory and tactile characteristics of female pollinator insects to such an extent that the males of these species are attracted, attempt to mate with the flower, and take pollen with them, which they will transfer to the flower of another plant without knowing it, by being lured once again. The Ophrys flower form therefore a set of ‘magic traits’ that play a key role in the speciation process. The high degree of specialisation in this plant-insect interaction is also thought to be a driving force underlying the rate of diversification observed in Ophrys. But these plants have other characteristics that could favour their diversification. Firstly, the still incomplete reproductive barriers between most species in the genus allow a certain amount of gene flow between lineages. It is increasingly well documented that these genetic exchanges can be responsible for the acquisition of adaptive variation in groups undergoing evolutionary radiation. Secondly, Ophrys have a large genome (&gt; 5 Gbp) with a complex composition (more than 70% transposable elements) that could provide raw material for generating variation, a source of biological innovation, but the study of which represents a technical challenge. Ophrys therefore present a rare and perhaps unique opportunity to study the early stages of speciation right up to the most remarkable evolutionary radiations, by providing a biological system that combines three ingredients that are particularly favourable to the diversification of lineages. In ORIGAMIS, we propose to implement a highly integrative approach based on multi-omic data (genomics, transcriptomics, metabolomics, phenomics and fitness proxies) to study the genomic architecture of magic traits and their impact on population divergence, as well as the contribution of adaptive introgression in Ophrys aveyronensis, a species with a disjunct geographic distribution for which we have been able to highlight islands of genomic divergence at different spatial and taxonomic scales. This system can therefore be used to study the consequences of parallel adaptation to different ecological conditions in a ‘simplified’ geographical context, following a relatively recent vicariance. We would like to test whether these islands of divergence could correspond to structural variants (in particular chromosomal inversions) and, if so, whether these regions where recombination is reduced could host loci functioning as supergenes and whose expression produces pleiotropic effects on several traits of the floral phenotype (morphology, colouration, odour) and indirectly on the ability of individuals to survive and reproduce. Innovative phenotyping of plants using 3D scanners will make it possible to quantify the flower in an exhaustive way, producing long-term data, free from experimenter bias. Analyses using Artificial Intelligence will be employed to identify the most relevant variables and analyse them. Finally, we will study whether these islands of divergence formed de novo or could have been acquired by introgressive hybridisation from sympatric congenic species. This project could thus contribute to the emergence of a promising new biological model for linking the processes at work at micro-evolutionary scales and studying their consequences at the scale of adaptive radiations, based for the first time on whole-genome resequencing and phenomics, on a taxon that lends itself well to scientific popularisation and participatory science initiatives.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/anr-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/anr-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/anr-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/anr.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[ANR ORIGAMIS]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ANR JCJC funded</title><link href="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2024/anr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ANR JCJC funded"/><published>2024-01-01T00:00:01+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-01T00:00:01+00:00</updated><id>https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2024/anr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yannbourgeois.github.io/blog/2024/anr/"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to report that our ANR project, DaTEPalm, has been funded. This project will work on obtaining a diversity panel of palms sequenced with ONT/Nanopore, focusing on polymorphic transposable elements (TEs). The funding covers a PhD and a post-doctoral researcher. The official summary is reproduced below, and can be found <a href="https://anr.fr/Project-ANR-23-CE20-0017">here</a>.</p> <p>The interaction between transposable elements (TEs) and their hosts is one of the most intricate co-evolutionary processes found in nature. Quantifying how TEs impact their host’s fitness has practical relevance in relation to real-world applications, such as understanding the molecular bases of selected phenotypes, or assessing mutational load in crops (so-called “cost of domestication”). The following project will focus on the impact of TEs on the host’s fitness, using the date palm (Phoenix dactylifera) as a model. This crop is of major economic and social importance in the Middle East and Northern Africa, and its consumption keeps rising every year. However, it is also threatened by more frequent droughts and increasing salinity due to climate change. A precise characterization of its genetic diversity is therefore essential to understand the adaptability of this species to growing environmental pressures. The project will use genomic data to examine the role of polymorphic TEs in selection and differentiation of date palm varieties across the species range. It will revolve around two questions: What is the distribution of TEs fitness effects in date palms? Can this distribution be predicted from functional genomic features such as gene regulatory networks? We will develop and apply new methods in population genomics to estimate the fraction of advantageous and harmful polymorphic TEs. We will compare results with de novo functional annotations of chromatin organization and regulatory networks to draw a comprehensive view of TEs’ impact on a keystone perennial species of agronomic interest for both developed and developing countries.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm-4 mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/anr-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/anr-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/anr-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/anr.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" title="example image" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="sample-posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="code"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Start of the DaTEPalm ANR JCJC project]]></summary></entry></feed>